The next section that we're going to cover
is free radical injury.
And the way this fits into the chapter
is that we've been talking about cellular injury
and we discussed hypoxia as one of the important causes
of cellular injury.
And of course, we used hypoxia as a mechanism
to teach some of the principles that a cell undergoes
when it becomes injured.
So we're now going to continue with our discussion of injury.
However, instead, we're gonna focus on free radicals,
which can also cause injury.
These are relatively, this discussion is relatively high yield
and hence the reason why I've made it a separate
sort of subsection in your text.
All right, before we can begin our discussion of free radicals,
we should take a step back
and define what a free radical actually is.
So a free radical is a chemical species
with an unpaired electron in the outer orbit.
And it's this unpaired electron that has the ability to induce damage within the cell.
Now, it's important to recognize that free radicals are actually generated physiologically
and pathologically.
So what do we mean by physiologically?
Well, physiologic generation of free radicals occurs during oxidative phosphorylation.
And of course, this is part of the normal physiology of a human being.
So that's why we use the term physiologic.
Now, let's review oxidative phosphorylation briefly
and remind ourselves that during oxidative phosphorylation,
cytochrome C oxidase transfers electrons to oxygen as a final electron acceptor.
And you recall in our prior discussion of the electron transport chain,
oxygen obviously accepts electrons,
which then drives the production of a proton gradient,
which then eventually drives the production of ATP.
Now, generally speaking, oxygen will actually accept four electrons.
And after accepting four electrons, water will be generated.
And so if during the sequence of accepting of electrons,
oxygen is partially reduced and doesn't receive all four electrons,
then free radicals can be generated.
But in order to understand the free radicals that are generated,
we do have to review a little bit of biochemistry.
So let's take a moment to just remind ourselves that if this is oxygen here,
if oxygen accepts one electron,
then it becomes something called superoxide.
If it accepts two electrons,
it then becomes hydrogen peroxide.
If it accepts three electrons,
it becomes hydroxyl ion.
And if it becomes,
if it accepts four electrons,
it becomes water.
And so when I say that physiologic generation of free radicals
occurs during oxidative phosphorylation,
obviously if there is a partial reduction of oxygen
so that it only accepts one, two, or three electrons
instead of the normal four electrons,
that's going to result in the production of free radicals.
And that does happen physiologically.
Free radicals can also be generated pathologically.
Some important examples,
ionizing radiation can generate free radicals.
And ionizing radiation,
the classic free radical that's generated,
is actually hydroxyl ion,
so OH.
And what's important to remember,
to recall here is that ionizing radiation,
the way by which it generates these free radicals
is that the radiation actually hits water within tissues.
And once it hits water within tissues,
one possible consequence of that
is the generation of hydroxyl free radical.
And we should bear in mind that
among all of the free radicals,
the hydroxyl free radical is sort of the most damaging.
And that's something that examiners like you to know.
So again, I'll repeat it.
Of all of the free radicals,
the hydroxyl free radical is the most damaging.
Now, another mechanism by which free radicals can be generated
or are generated actually is inflammation.
Remind ourselves that when neutrophils come in to battle an infection,
they have two mechanisms of killing the microbe.
One is called oxygen-dependent.
The other is oxygen-independent.
Remember that the oxygen-dependent mechanism starts out,
if you go back to biochemistry,
the reaction starts out with something called an oxidative burst.
And basically what happens there is that oxygen is taken,
and oxygen is acted on by an enzyme.
And do you remember the name of that enzyme?
It's important for biochemistry, high yield for examinations.
The enzyme is called NADPH oxidase.
And NADPH oxidase takes oxygen and converts it to superoxide.
And so that's the very first step.
And superoxide will very quickly be converted by superoxide dismutase to hydrogen peroxide,
and then hydrogen peroxide is converted by myeloperoxidase to form bleach, or HOCl.
But we'll discuss the additional reactions later when we do our chapter or section on inflammation.
However, what I really want to highlight here is this very first reaction.
That first reaction in an oxygen-dependent killing generates free radical,
and so in particular the superoxide free radical.
And so inflammation is another mechanism by which free radicals are formed.
A third pathologic mechanism by which free radicals can form
is by interaction with metals, for example, copper and iron.
And this actually becomes very high yield as well.
The reason we have to be familiar with this is because,
well, why don't we take a step back.
First of all, let's remind ourselves from biochemistry
that generally speaking, copper and iron are tightly,
are usually whenever present in the body, are usually bound.
Just to give you an example,
I mean, you're all familiar with the headaches of learning about iron biochemistry
and the concept of, you know, ferritin and transferrin
and all these molecules that iron gets bound to the moment that it enters the blood.
The reason iron is so carefully bound the moment it enters the blood
is because if iron is left free,
it has the ability to generate free radicals.
And the way by which it generates the free radical,
there's an important reaction, the name of which you should be aware of.
It's called the Fenton reaction.
And the Fenton reaction allows for iron to actually generate a free radical.
And the free radical that is most commonly generated is hydroxyl free radical.
And again, hydroxyl free radical is the most dangerous of all of the free radicals.
Maybe it'd be easier for you to remember if we just,
or at least for an examination, perhaps another important point here,
which will help you remember this concept,
is we have a couple diseases in which either copper can build up
or in which iron can build up.
And in both of those diseases, when copper and iron build up,
we get various clinical manifestations.
Let's just take iron, for example.
When iron builds up, we get a disease called hemochromatosis.
And you're well aware of the fact that hemochromatosis,
when hemochromatosis results in tissue damage, for example,
can create cirrhosis in the liver and damage in other tissues.
And that's the reason or the underlying mechanism behind that tissue damage
is actually the fact that that excess iron in the body
that's seen in hemochromatosis actually generates free radicals.
Another example, I just take an excess of copper.
So what's the disease in which there is an excess of copper?
It's called Wilson's disease.
And in Wilson's disease, the excess of copper generates free radicals,
which then leads to tissue damage,
creating a certain clinical, a series or set of certain clinical symptoms.
So again, it's important to know,
and examiners love to go after the, to ask you,
what's the underlying mechanism of damage in hemochromatosis,
or what's the underlying mechanism of damage in, um, in Wilson's disease.
In both cases, it's the pathologic generation of free radicals
that actually results in the tissue damage
that then produces clinical symptoms.
All right, another example of pathologic generation of free radicals
are drugs and chemicals.
Acetaminophen is a, is a very kind of classic example,
especially from pharmacology.
Acetaminophen, um, goes to the liver.
It gets converted by the P450 system.
And, uh, free radicals are, are generated in the process.
Um, the, the free radicals can be damaging to the tissues.
And you, you're, you will have learned,
or perhaps have already learned,
that high dose, um, acetaminophen can be,
or acetaminophen can be taken by a patient, uh,
who might try to commit suicide, for example,
or who may overdose on acetaminophen.
And that overdose of acetaminophen causes massive liver necrosis.
And the massive liver necrosis is due to the fact
that the acetaminophen gets into the liver,
the hepatocytes convert it,
and in the process, free radicals are generated.
And so that results in, in damage in the liver.
Um, a, a chemical that can cause, uh, free radical,
um, or a classic chemical that can become a free radical
is carbon tetrachloride.
And carbon tetrachloride, I'm going to discuss in much more detail
in a moment, because it lends to a high-yield principle
that shows up on exam.
So we'll, we'll, let's put that one aside for a moment,
and we'll discuss it, again, in just a few slides.
Um, what's the problem with free radicals?
I mean, so what?
If you get a free radical, how?
It, I've told you it injures the cell, but how?
So, uh, free radicals can do a couple things.
Number one, they peroxidize lipids,
and that is damaging, particularly, to the lipid membrane.
Uh, and number two, they have the ability to oxidize,
and in particular, they can oxidize, oxidize DNA and proteins.
The oxid, oxidation of proteins will result in, um, in, in,
in damage to the cell.
And also, the oxidation of DNA can result in damage to the cell.
And this is important because it's particularly implicated
in oncogenesis.
What's oncogenesis?
The, the formation of cancers.
Um, remember that cancers are formed by mutations in DNA.
Okay, and if there's a, uh, if there's oxidation of DNA,
that would introduce mutations within DNA,
and so it would increase, it would, it could potentially cause cancer.
And, and this is the whole idea behind, uh, uh, for example,
if you walk into a vitamin store, or you look at an advertisement for vitamins,
where they say that, uh, you know, antioxidants and other things
that fight off free radicals can prevent aging and protect you from cancer,
and that's because there's, uh, there's an understanding that, um,
that free radicals have the ability to damage DNA, which, uh, which can, um,
lead to an increased risk for cancer, and they also have the ability to damage the cell,
which can potentially add to, uh, or lead to, let's say, be a component of aging.
Now, because free radicals are so damaging, and because they're generated physiologically,
it only makes sense that the body would have a mechanism of eliminating the free radicals
so that damage would not occur, especially since they're generated physiologically.
So, of, of course, if we're going to generate them physiologically,
then we need to be able to eliminate them as well.
There are actually three major mechanisms by which, uh, free radicals can be eliminated.
The first are antioxidants, and antioxidants, um, include things like, um,
vitamin A, vitamin C, vitamin E, um, these are your classic antioxidants,
and, and they have the ability to, to, um, to eliminate free radicals.
Um, another, uh, important mechanism of elimination of free radicals,
I'm going to skip here and go a little out of order, but it's metal carrier proteins.
Um, metal carrier proteins are what I've already talked about.
You, you know that copper and iron have the ability to create free radicals,
iron in particular, by the Fenton reaction, um,
and the generation of free radicals, um, is, is a dangerous thing.
And so, the way by which the body handles that is to have metal carrier proteins.
For example, transferrin in the blood, which tightly binds iron to deliver it to the liver and the macrophages.
And you know that when iron is actually bound in, um, macrophages or within the liver,
it's actually tightly bound to a molecule called ferritin.
And so, these metal carrier proteins, they protect, uh, they basically hide away the metals
so that free radicals are not generated.
The third category of, um, of, um, substances that can eliminate free radicals are enzymes.
Now, the reason why I sort of take on this category last is because there's a little detail here
from biochemistry that examiners expect you to be familiar with.
So, let's, let's briefly talk about, um, the enzymes.
There are three major enzymes.
Each of them is relatively high yield that are important for the elimination of free radicals.
Um, I, I think that the easy way for me, at least, to, to, to remember these is to go back
and just create that same biochemical, um, paradigm that I highlighted earlier,
where oxygen, if it accepts one electron, um, it becomes superoxide.
So, superoxide is an important free radical to be familiar with.
Uh, super, if it were to accept another electron from here, it would become hydrogen peroxide,
H2O2, which is another important free radical to be familiar with.
Hydrogen peroxide, were it to, were it to accept another electron, for example, would, um,
would actually become hydroxyl free radical.
Sorry, hydroxyl free radical.
And obviously this could eventually generate water.
Um, now, I use this paradigm to help me to remember, um, the, each of the free radicals,
because these are the three key free radicals that you must be familiar with from biochemistry.
And then I use this paradigm to remind me of, um, the enzymes,
because each of these free radicals here, the one, you know, the three that I've drawn here,
are actually each handled by one, uh, particular enzyme, or predominantly by one enzyme.
So, the first one is easy.
This is, this one is superoxide, and guess who handles this?
Superoxide dismutase.
So, superoxide dismutase actually takes out superoxide.
Um, hydrogen peroxide is, um, is handled by catalase.
All right.
Oops, it's handled by catalase.
And then hydroxyl free radical, um, they, the, one of the major mechanisms by which this,
uh, free radicals actually removed is glutathione peroxidase.
Um, and glutathione peroxidase is an enzyme that takes the assistance of glutathione,
which is an antioxidant, um, and, uh, glutathione, um, will be very important, uh,
later in our discussions of, um, uh, in our discussions of anemia.
And you'll, you'll hear about that when we talk about anemia,
so I won't, uh, get into too much detail here.
However, it is important to know these three, the, the, the three key free radicals,
again, superoxide, hydrogen peroxide, and hydroxyl free radical.
It's important to know that hydroxyl free radical is the most damaging,
or the most sort of dangerous of the three free radicals.
And then it's important to know what enzymes, um, disrupt or, or handle each of those free radicals.
And clearly superoxide would be handled by superoxide dismutase,
and hydrogen peroxide by catalase,
and then hydroxyl free radical by glutathione peroxidase.
All right. Now, to, to close off this discussion,
we want to talk about two very high-yield, um, examples of free radical injury
that often show up on an examination.
So, the first is carbon tetrachloride.
And carbon tetrachloride is, was classically seen in the dry cleaning industry.
So, uh, a clinical vignette might say that the person is exposed to the dry,
the chemicals of dry cleaning industry.
Now, carbon tetrachloride, um, happens to get into the blood,
and when it gets into the blood, it gets converted to something called carbon trichloride.
It's converted by carbon trichloride, which is a free radical.
It's converted by, it's converted to carbon trichloride in the P450 system of the liver.
That's important.
In the P450 system of the liver.
Once it's converted to carbon trichloride, that's now a free radical,
and that damages the, uh, the hepatocytes.
The initial stage of damage will actually be reversible,
and the key sign of reversible damage will be cellular swelling.
When the cell swells up, um, one of the consequences will be that the endoplasmic,
the rough endoplasmic reticulum, uh, will also swell,
and when that swells, ribosomes will pop off,
and protein synthesis will be reduced.
Now, if protein synthesis is reduced,
then you need to take a step back and just think about your biochemistry
and physiology and histology, etc.,
and remind yourself that, um, one of the very important functions of the liver
is to gather fat, particularly from the diet,
and then to bring, and then to repackage it and send it back out.
Now, the repackaging of fat actually occurs by binding up the molecules of cholesterol and lipids
to, um, uh, via apolipoproteins.
Um, remember that if you're going to produce, um, the, the, um,
you're going to be able to produce the, uh, the, not the molecule,
but the substance that's going to carry, um, fat and cholesterol,
you're going to need apolipoproteins.
So, if carbon tetrachloride damages the liver cell and causes swelling,
and swelling causes, uh, loss of rough,
or loss of the ribosomes on the endoplasmic reticulum,
which then causes a decrease in protein synthesis,
the decrease in protein synthesis will then eventually result in lack of apolipoproteins.
Lack of apolipoproteins means that fat comes into the liver but can't get out.
So, guess what the classic histologic finding will be?
Fatty change in the liver.
And that's very, very high yield.
Uh, because this goes back to a total tracing of, um,
or a total retracing of the biochemistry behind cellular, cellular injury.
So, let me show you a picture.
This is a classic image.
Uh, this, these are hepatocytes.
Each of these individual cells are, are hepatocytes.
And you can clearly see that there are all these circular spaces within these hepatocytes.
And these circular spaces represent the accumulation of fat,
which is called fatty liver.
Now, uh, again, the fatty liver is, uh, occurs, or the, we can say the mechanism of the fatty liver here,
is decreased protein synthesis.
In particular, decreased proteins, decreased synthesis of apolipoproteins,
so that fat begins to accumulate in the cells and really can't be transported out of the cells.
Um, and so that's something to be very familiar with.
Again, relatively high yield.
I'm going to take you a step back, or one slide back.
And now, finally, end off this discussion with, uh, with, with another example of free radical injury,
which is called reperfusion injury.
The idea behind reperfusion injury is that, um, when you cut the blood supply to,
let's say that the blood supply is cut off to an organ, um, I don't know, just take the heart, for example,
the cardiac, sorry, the coronary artery gets secluded, there's a myocardial infarction,
and the tissue begins to die.
Now, once the tissue dies, um, the cell membrane is going to be damaged, right?
That's the hallmark of irreversible injury, cell membrane damage,
and enzymes will begin to leak out into the blood.
In particular, the, the troponins are sort of the gold standard enzyme, um,
cardiac troponins that will actually leak out into the blood.
Now, uh, as those enzymes leak out into the blood,
there will be an indication that there has been irreversible injury to the cells.
If, um, the blood is returned to the, um, organ,
let's say that the patient goes to the cath lab and they open up the, the artery,
and when they open up the artery, blood goes back to the organ,
one of the, um, interesting consequences of returning blood to the organ
is that once blood returns to the organ,
now oxygen has also returned to the organ,
and inflammatory cells have also returned to the organ,
and the combination of the inflammatory cells, uh, reacting against the dead tissue,
along with the presence of oxygen, can actually generate free radicals.
And the generation of free radicals can then further damage the, um,
the, the cardiac myocytes in the example of the heart.
And so what'll happen are the classic clinical vignette that, that occurs,
or that can be given, is that there's a patient, they get an MI,
the cardiac enzymes are going up, um, they're taken to the cardiac cath lab,
and, um, the artery is opened, and after the artery is opened,
the cardiac enzymes continue to rise.
Now why do the cardiac enzymes continue to rise?
They continue to rise because once the blood is returned,
the blood contains oxygen and inflammatory cells,
and that's going to result in a generation of free radicals,
which is then going to, uh, going to, um,
allow for continued injury to actually occur to the myocardium.
And that's called a reperfusion injury, i.e., injury that arises due to reperfusion.
So classic vignette is a continued elevation in cardiac enzymes
after opening or returning of the blood supply to the region,
and it is basically due to free radical generation.
So that closes off this section.